The Chinese are going to
use cigarettes
to help
bail out the
country's banks, and more
importantly, insurance
companies.  And yes, this is a
sentence I
thought I would never
say, and no, it's not a joke
.  They are using
tobacco and the proceeds from
it to
recapitalize
some of the largest
banks and insurance
companies, because China is in
a mess that is only
growing, and it is
September, which means
bazooka season there.
The past "bazookas" didn't
work, they didn't
fire the way
everyone expected,
at least not the way
everyone expected.  So,
China is left with
few really good
or even
realistic
options.  So, as they
continue with the
bank recapitalization plan, they are
facing
budget
constraints, there is a
lot to
talk about here.  So,
last weekend
it was reported that
the Chinese are going to
inject the equivalent of
$45 billion into
some of their
biggest banks
to, as the Western
mainstream says,
stimulate
growth.  This is not about
stimulating
growth.  It's about the
Chinese being trapped
in a low-
income trap, a
low-interest
rate trap, and a pile of hidden, bad loans on the balance sheets of
Chinese banks
.  And, as we will
focus here, also in
insurance companies.
Although we'll get to that in a
moment.  So,
you know, the
common
idea is that
it's another incentive,
even though it's not really an
incentive, because it doesn't
stimulate.  But from the
Chinese
government's perspective, it means: "
Hey, the situation
keeps
getting worse."
The economy continues
to slow
more than everyone
expected.
The banking sector,
which we recently
talked about and
reported on in a video not
long ago,
cut
lending
by the most in
history in July.  And yes, July
is not the best month
for lending, but it's
not just about July,
especially when you see
the statistics we'll
look at here.
Lending to
households
has declined significantly.
So they have to
do something.  As I said
, September is the season of "
bazookas", and this is the last
of them, which only
continues the previous ones.
It's not so much about
stimulating
growth as it is
about trying to stop the
decline before
it becomes increasingly
dangerous.  And before
we get to
that, I want to make something very
clear.
Whenever you
talk about negativity
in China, people hear
one of two things.  There are "
China bulls" who
say that China is
bypassing all
competitors.  This will be the
century of the Chinese.
They are a dragon with
a thousand-year
perspective, and
everyone else here has a
short memory, and
China will simply
be ahead of everyone.
This won't
even come close.  As well as
the opposite.  The other
side says, "Okay,
if China is not
going to
dominate, that
means it has to
completely collapse
."  So when someone
talks about a
negative
outlook for China,
they mean
that the government will fall,
the economy will completely
depreciate, and the entire
system and country will
fall apart.  That's
not what we're
talking about either.  We say
that the situation in China
is becoming increasingly difficult,
leading to a
further downturn in both the
banking sector
and the real
economy.  In fact,
these two things are now
combined, which is why we are
talking here about
cigarettes and
investments in the
tobacco industry.  So
, the recession in China is not a
complete and final
collapse.  This is economic
growth that
continues
to slow,
largely due to a
banking crisis that is
slowly smoldering beneath the
surface.  This is one piece of
evidence that
the situation is getting
serious, as China
continues to pour
money into the banking
sector, and now into
insurance companies.
They announced that
they would help
recapitalize
eight institutions,
including the Industrial
and Commercial Bank of
China, the
Agricultural
Bank of China, and
several others that
we will talk about soon.
These are big banks.    A
significant portion
of loans is concentrated
in small and medium-sized
banks.  So again
, the point is to
capitalize the
big banks, perhaps
to make them
act like “bad
banks,” because they are
also saddled with a
pile of bad
debt, so they
need additional
capital to
maintain
sufficient reserves and prevent the
banking sector credit crunch from turning
into a liquidity crisis,
which is unlikely
, but still possible.
So, fundraising: you
see
Bloomberg reporting 300 billion
yuan from
the Ministry of
Finance as a
government contribution, a
total of 360 billion
yuan from all sources,
of which 60 billion
remains.  A significant
portion of these funds
come from the
China National Tobacco Corporation, which actually
makes more sense than it
seems at first
glance.  China National Tobacco
is one of the most
profitable companies
not only in China, not
only in the tobacco
industry, but perhaps
the most profitable
company on planet
Earth.  China has a
huge problem with
smoking.  There
are about
300-400 million
active smokers there, which is
simply an incredible
number, and they
continue to smoke,
despite the fact that the rest of
the world, or at least a
significant part of it,
is turning away from
cigarettes in favor of
vaping and other
alternative
methods of smoking.
So, the Chinese
tobacco monopoly, a
state system or a
state-owned company,
has huge
assets.
The Chinese are now becoming
increasingly cautious
and vigilant about
their own fiscal
situation, which is one
reason they
have begun to crack down on
tax evasion among the
ultra-rich—a different
story that I
wrote about in our
in-depth analysis at
Euro Dollar University.  But
in many ways, they
also want to be
careful about
how much money they
borrow through these
special bonds
and what they put
those funds toward, such as
recapitalizing the
banking system.
So it's no wonder they
can knock on
China Tobacco's door and
say, "Hey, you
know, you're killing
a lot of our
citizens.  We
need some of that
money you have
been saving from your
huge incomes and
profits to
help
the banking sector
.”  Maybe we can
help clear up the
real estate mess and
maintain relative
stability before
things get
really
bad.  So, this is a
completely logical
connection.  China Tobacco has
a lot of money and
high profitability
.  It
can certainly afford to
help the
Chinese government with
its latest
bank recapitalization scheme, which, as I
said, is no longer
just a
bank recapitalization scheme.  This is probably the
most important
development here.
Note
the names at the end of the list:
China Life Insurance, China Taiping
Insurance, and China Reinsurance.
Although the amounts are not
colossal, the fact
that some of China's largest
insurance companies
are on this
list and receiving
capital indicates
that China
is aware of the
problem in the
insurance sector as well.
Not only bad
loans in banks, but also
potential problems
hidden in the balance sheets of
insurance companies.  And
where have we heard about this before?
The search for higher
returns may
not be just an
American or
European phenomenon.
It seems that in China, too, there
was a search for
high
returns while
taking
huge risks.
So, the standard
explanation is
that China is
recapitalizing
insurance companies
through lower
interest rates.
Therefore, potential
yields,
nominal returns
on safe
assets, continue to
fall, which means
that the level of
interest coverage on
China's future obligations is
also falling.  Therefore,
some
recapitalization is needed.  It's
solely because of...Oh, it's
all because of interest
rates.  This is not about,
you know, this is not about
hidden bad
loans in
insurance companies' portfolios.
Although last week
China's financial regulator rewrote
some of its
outdated, indeed
ancient, laws
for the first time since 1995.  They
have strengthened control over
shareholder interests.  They
set higher
minimum
capital thresholds.  This effectively
means that
regulators
have adjusted some of
the rules because
they may
have detected behavior
that closely resembles what
we've been
talking about here: private
loans, private
equity, and insurance
companies hidden in
Cayman
Islands subsidiaries owned by
other
subsidiaries of
insurers.  So,
risky behavior
.  It is not difficult to
conclude that in
the pursuit of
profitability,
taking on more
risks than was
reasonable and necessary
given the economic
and financial
situation in China, the
portfolios of insurance
companies have now
come under
suspicion and scrutiny from
regulators due to
questionable, junk
lending practices
that may have taken
place in the insurance
business.  Because let's face it
: in China, the economy,
as I said,
continues to
deteriorate, and
Chinese insurance
companies, perhaps not to the
same extent as
Japanese ones, still
have a lot of
liabilities.  They still
have a huge
need to generate
profits.  And
interest rates in
China have not only been falling for
the last two years,
they have been falling for 15
years.  So, as
interest rates
continue to
fall for
fundamental
reasons, not
policy, it leads to what
many
have called a
zero-rate trap, where
financial firms, with
low rates,
can't...well, I'll
get to that in a
second.  Let's
talk about
insurance companies.  Hmm
.  The fact that the Chinese
have announced the
recapitalization of both
insurance companies and
banks is not a
positive signal.  This is
not stimulation.  It's
not like in 2024, when
all the Western media
went crazy over the "
big bazooka."  It's
more of a "oh
my god, they have to
do it again" kind of thing.  And
now they're
going to do
it for insurance
companies.  This is
actually not a very
good sign.  So,
despite the fact that this was supposed to
be a strong
stimulus,
you saw that the
market reaction,
at least the stock
market in China, was
somewhat negative.  She
was not positive.
It certainly wasn't like that
in September 2024.
It was more like "oh-
oh," they have to
keep
bailing out the banking
sector.  Now they are
going to start
bailing out some of the
biggest insurance
companies.  This does
n't sound
optimistic at all, because
it's actually
not positive at all.  This is
another sign that
the situation in China is
getting worse or
serious,
which is what we have been talking about all this time
.  The more
they feel they have to
do, the
worse things get, you know
.  And the more
they feel like they have to
do the
same thing they did
before, the better you
understand that
it didn't work before and that
they still have a lot to
do because the situation
isn't improving and isn't
moving forward.
And you may remember
that we went through this
last year.
Last year wasn't
exactly
bazooka season.  This was
actually before
we got to the "
bazooka" season, sometime during the
tariff period.
Early last
year, in the spring, the
Chinese government, as
they announced in
September 2024 as
part of the "
bazooka" package, borrowed a bunch of
money in the
bond market, took that
money and
recapitalized—I'm
using quotes—
recapitalized
Chinese banks.  Then
only banks.  And
apparently it didn't
work, because now
they're doing it again
.  Furthermore, we know
from
Chinese bank statistics
how successful
this
recapitalization and
all the incentives have been, because
as I mentioned at the
very beginning,
lending volumes
in China in July,
according to total
social
financing,
showed the largest
reduction in
history.  So, this is not
an incentive.  It's, "
Hey, let's
try to
recapitalize the
banks and insurance
companies to
try to
stabilize
lending, borrowing,
and debt throughout the
Chinese system,"
because it
keeps going in the
wrong
direction.  The situation
is getting worse, not
better.  And the
worse it gets, the
more the government
has to do, which
is the right
way to perceive
stimulus.  They are not
stimulating.  It is
a response to problems
that are already happening,
and problems that have become
so serious
that even government
bureaucrats,
economists, and sometimes
central bankers are
reacting to them.  And the
credit data in
China is getting pretty
grim, if not
downright scary,
which brings us back
to the question: why are they
recapitalizing
banks and insurance
companies?  This is because
debt is no longer even
close to its
trend.  It
deviated from
the trend in 2024,
hence the "bazooka"
at the end of 2024, but
it obviously didn't
work, because in
early 2025 there was a
small surge
that many
attributed to the events of
2024, but it didn't
last long.  And by
mid-2025,
the situation began
to deteriorate again,
and not just in
China's banking or debt sectors, but also in the real
economy.  So, it becomes
clear that in
2026 the situation with
lending and the
banking sector
is moving in the completely
wrong
direction.  Hence the
latest brilliant
ideas with "bazookas" from
Beijing.  Now we have
insurance companies, and
I guarantee it's
not just about
interest rates.
But what do
interest
rates really say?  Interest
rates are a
fundamental
reflection of
expectations for
growth and
inflation, embedded in
bond market prices.  So, the
more the
bond market and
financial participants
in general are concerned about
economic
risks,
financial risks
, banking
risks, or
liquidity risks, whatever they may be
.  And in the
case of China,
at least three of these
four risks
are present, except perhaps
liquidity risk.  But
understanding that three out of
four of these risks
are huge,
interest rates
continue to fall.
Since Chinese
banks and insurance
companies, which
have lent to state-owned
entities for the
past 15 years,
starting in 2009 and even
earlier, especially
after the 2009, 2012
and 2016 stimulus packages,
own a huge
portion of this debt,
the situation is not
improving and
China's economy
continues to decline
, which means lower
expectations for growth
and inflation.  Lower
expectations for
growth and
inflation lead
to lower
interest rates, as
you see here.  They do not
stimulate
lending, they are
a reaction to the
weakness
of lending and the
weakness of the system.
So rates are
going down, which is causing
Chinese banks
to lose profits,
insurance companies to lose profits
, which is making their
situation even
riskier,
forcing banks
to cut back on
lending even
more, which leads to
further
rate cuts because the
bond market says, "Well,
the banks are cutting back."
This is a sign of weakness
and difficulty, so the
rates fall even
lower.  And you see how
it all
becomes a
vicious cycle.  Rates are
falling,
banking sector profitability
is declining, “bad”
loans continue
to accumulate,
rates are falling even
lower, “bad”
loans are increasing, and the
profitability of
Chinese banks and
insurance companies is
falling.  They fell
into a trap.  So the
lower the rates, the
more difficult it becomes, and the
more difficulties it
creates for the
banking sector
, hence the latest
recapitalization.  It's
all part of the
big picture: when
you can
interpret
interest rates correctly,
rather than seeing them as a
stimulus, it all makes
perfect sense.  And it
continues to move in the
wrong direction.  "
Down" is the wrong
direction.  Especially in the
household sector.  I don't
think people
really realize
how complicated
the situation has become.    The
household sector is on
the front lines.  Chinese
banks don't want
to lend, and
Chinese
households and
companies don't want
to borrow.  Right now, all you hear in the media is
that
Chinese
households have
insufficient demand for
loans, but as we
see, the Chinese
government, through its
regulators, understands
that not only is
the demand for Chinese
loans falling, but also their
supply.  But if you
combine these two
factors, looking
at the period from January to
July 2026, this is the
most recent data
we have, because the August
statistics are not yet
out.  From January to
July, household loans
fell by nearly a
trillion yuan,
more than three-
quarters of a trillion.
Household lending has fallen and shrunk.  This
compares to the first
seven months of
last year, after the
September "bazooka" of
2024, with a figure of
plus 680 billion.  This
plus 660 billion
caused
concern
last year, which is why
they carried out
recapitalization and
other stimulus
measures in 2025.  But
the move from 680
billion positive
to 819 billion
negative is a
major change between
last year and this year.  And
we know exactly when
it happened—in June
and July of last
year.  So there was a
huge shift in
household lending,
compared to 1.25
trillion positive in
2024, which, by the way,
was also not very
good.  1.25 trillion is what
ultimately
led to the “bazooka”
in September 2024.  Because
if we go back to
2023, there were
3.06 trillion.  It was
a little overstated because of
that big moon
that you see on the
chart, or the
huge bar
going up—the period of
economic opening.
There was some
lending that
only happened because it had been
postponed earlier.  In
any case, 3.06
trillion
is probably an inflated figure.
It was a more usual,
typical first
half of the year, the first 7
months of the year—
about 2 trillion,
but in any case:
3 trillion, then 1.25
trillion, then 680
billion, and finally
minus 819 billion.
Yes.  China has problems
in the banking
sector.  And also
problems with
borrowing.  We've
talked about this before—I
discussed this with
Steve on a YouTube video
a while back, I
think a couple of weeks
ago—about how China
is trying to
save the
real estate sector from the
demand side, for example
by introducing a 40-
year mortgage, which,
let's be honest, is
kind of a "
desperate move
," because a 40-year mortgage
doesn't
make the payments much cheaper.
However, what it does do is
create more
interest
charges at the very
beginning, especially in the
first few years,
which is a kind of small
gift to the
banking sector
.  So even here it all
comes down to
Chinese banks,
insurance companies,
and Chinese
debt markets.
It's not just about
low demand for
loans.  It is also a matter of the
reluctance of
Chinese banks
to lend, hence
the recapitalization, which is
aimed not at
growth, but at
an attempt to stabilize
the situation in the
banking sector
, and also, apparently, in
insurance companies.
And you can see
why and how none of this
worked.  China is
allocating historic
amounts of funds to
rescue the housing
sector from 2024.  And since
June 2023,
house prices have fallen...
let me
get this straight.
Housing prices fell
almost every month.
However, housing prices,
according to the
average across 70
cities in China, have not
shown
a single positive
month since June 2023
.  There were a few
zeros,
but overall,
housing prices in China across
most of the country—there are
some islands of
stability, like in the
big
tier-one cities, but
for most of
China, the
real estate market
has been experiencing
price declines since June 2023.
It's been 3 years.  3 years and
house prices have fallen
11%, which, I
mean, may
not sound like much.  This
should sound like a
lot, but it may not
seem like it,
especially in 3 years.  What
is a couple of percent
per year?  But we
are talking about
housing prices.  Can you
imagine a 11% drop in
housing prices in the United
States?  We didn't
see anything
like this in 2008 and 2009
, not by 11%.  So
even though it's a
long, slow,
drawn-out process, an
11% drop in housing prices—yes, they have a
serious problem in
China.  So, yes,
there is a lack of demand
for loans, especially
mortgages, because you are
unlikely to want to
buy a house
whose price is falling year
after year.  Of course you
won't do that.
On the other hand, would
you want to issue
loans under such
conditions?  First, the
collateral against which you are
lending will
likely
depreciate
while you are lending,
not to mention the
risks associated with
such lending.
This explains why
interest rates
are low and why the Chinese
are trying
to save their
banking and
now insurance
sectors.  Again,
economic
statistics and
graphs show it
all.  Retail
sales
correlate well with the
home prices I
just talked about.  Actually
, I showed this
graph in one of
my videos last
month, in mid-
August, here on YouTube.  You
see that spending
has almost stopped in
nominal
terms,
there is
tremendous weakness,
which is quite logical.  This
also suggests
that the difficulties in the
real estate
and banking sectors are
indeed spreading
to the real economy,
especially consumer
spending and, consequently,
weak domestic
demand in China.    There is
really weak
domestic demand in
China, which leads
to all sorts of other
negative and
secondary effects.
Investments in
fixed assets;  What is
important in
investing in
fixed capital,
again, I will give
a few points.
First, this is part of
urgent measures
to stabilize the
banking sector
, as the Chinese
seek to
stabilize
fixed capital investment,
they want to
stabilize
the economy as a whole.
But the second point
is that
fixed capital investment is
falling not only in
construction, but is also
declining in
manufacturing, as well as
in general
infrastructure investment from
various sources.  So
investment in
fixed assets is a
more pressing
need, an incentive
to try to
stabilize the
financial situation,
not to
restore
China's growth, but to
try to eliminate
some of those
downside risks that
continue to arise
.  And to be clear
, again:
downside risk does not
necessarily mean,
or even likely
mean, that China
will collapse in a
fiery explosion, with
dust
flying everywhere
.  I don't know where
this metaphor came from.
But the risk of a slowdown in
China continues—not
just a risk,
the reality of a slowdown
in China continues
to manifest itself.  Therefore,
the government's goal is
to try to
stabilize
the situation to
prevent a chaotic
collapse.  And the risk of that
happening is
increasing, but I'll
come back to the
bond market, because it
really all starts with
growth,
interest rate fundamentals,
growth and
inflation
expectations.  The bond market
is already telling you that
past stimulus
didn't work,
future
stimulus
won't work either, and the
more
the Chinese do, the more the
bond market
gets
confirmation
that safety and
liquidity are the
right
investment
themes.  Chinese
banks are exiting
risky loans and
moving into
safe and liquid
instruments.  This is why
Chinese bond yields are
so low: the
banking sector
is stopping
lending and buying
government bonds,
even though they yield next to
nothing,
making the debt
trap on China's
balance sheet even tighter.
So the lower
bond yields get, the
worse the situation is,
because think about
the calculations of
Chinese
creditors, whether they are
insurance companies,
banks or even
individuals.  This
suggests that
they are willing to accept
virtually zero
nominal
returns, very
low yields
, less than 2%, for the sake of
safety and
liquidity, even
though they
need profits
to heal
their balance sheets.  Therefore,
the return on other
risk-adjusted opportunities,
lending to the
real sector of
the economy, should be
below 2%.  In other
words, it's very
likely that
Chinese banks,
financial firms, and
insurance companies
are looking at the
situation in China and
saying that the
risk-adjusted returns on risky transactions are
likely to be
negative, so much so
that I'm willing to own a
five-year
Chinese
bond
yielding 1.4%.  That's
how pathetic
these earnings are, but it's
also an extremely
useful commentary on the
situation in China—from
the macroeconomics all the way down to the
performance of insurance
companies and their
portfolios.  And just
to add something else:
look at how closely the
copper-
to-gold ratio correlates,
at least in general, with
Chinese bond yields
, which actually makes
sense if you understand
what the
ratio is indicating;  It has
recently risen
as copper
has appreciated and gold
has weakened, which for
some people
indicates a
potential
reflationary trend
emerging in the
copper market.  You know, the demand for
physical copper for AI
or whatever, maybe
China is coming back,
maybe the rest of the world
is starting
to grow again.  So,
copper prices are rising.
However, the
copper-to-gold ratio is
likely
to return to the level of
Chinese bond yields
, as there
is a
fundamental
relationship between the two.  Copper prices
only rose due to
the threat of tariffs, which
blocked
huge amounts of
copper inside the US,
cutting it off from the rest of the
global system.  This has
led to
another
supply shortage, which also
fits into the picture of
Chinese bond yields
and the overall
low
interest rate situation
in China.  It is quite
logical that the authorities
are trying to
recapitalize the
banking sector,
as well as the insurance
sector, due to
risky behavior
that is becoming increasingly
dangerous and
will soon be
exposed.  And third,
why are they
using
revenues from the tobacco
industry?  Because the
tobacco company
has a lot of money, and the
Chinese government is
coming to the point where it
understands: we are doing
too much, and we
need to look for
alternative
sources of
stimulation, which is
not really
stimulating, and which,
according to the market, will not have an
effect in the future.
Otherwise, interest
rates in China would
rise with the
copper-
to-gold ratio, rather than fall
against it.  And it's
not just about
Chinese government
bond yields, there are a number of
other signals
that confirm this.
So, the
copper to gold ratio now has a
life of its own.
It turns out that Chinese
cigarettes are saving
Chinese banks, because
they are overwhelmed with
bad
loans in a
bad economy, unable to
profitably clean up
their balance sheets.  Incidentally,
Chinese insurance
companies are also
likely to find themselves in
this predicament, which is entirely
logical, given their
tendency to seek
profitability through
increasingly absurd
methods.  So,
bailing out banks,
bailing out insurance
companies, cigarettes—
this is something you
probably wouldn't expect to
hear about today, but
it just goes to show that
the more they
have to do and
feel they have to
do, the worse
things actually are.
Thank you for joining
me.  See you soon
.